<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tommy Blanchard - Blog</title><link href="http://tommyblanchard.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://tommyblanchard.com/feeds/blog.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://tommyblanchard.com/</id><updated>2017-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Retrospective on leaving academia for industry data science</title><link href="http://tommyblanchard.com/retrospective-on-leaving-academia-for-industry-data-science" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tommy Blanchard</name></author><id>tag:tommyblanchard.com,2017-04-09:/retrospective-on-leaving-academia-for-industry-data-science</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been two and a half months since I left academia to take a job as a data scientist in industry. Although I haven't been in my new job for very long yet, I wanted to check in with my current thoughts about whether the transition was worth it and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been two and a half months since I left academia to take a job as a data scientist in industry. Although I haven't been in my new job for very long yet, I wanted to check in with my current thoughts about whether the transition was worth it and the differences between working in academia and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a lot of ways, being an industry data scientist is a lot like being a post-doc. I'm paid to tackle intellectual problems, I have a lot of freedom in how I approach problems, and there is emphasis placed on professional development (attending conferences, etc.). Of course, there is a change of emphasis on what types of tasks I do - as an academic I spent a lot of time collecting data and writing, in industry the emphasis is more on doing analyses and communicating results verbally or through simple reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problems I had in academia I no longer have in industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the decision to do leave academia for a number of reasons, outlined in a &lt;a href="http://tommyblanchard.com/reasons-i-left-academia"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. The main reasons were that I was lonely, stressed out, and no longer found the research held any interest for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in industry, there's a lot less social isolation. It's rare that a day goes by where I'm not in some kind of meeting. While sometimes this can get frustrating when meetings seem unnecessary, I think a big part of the point of meetings is social. It's nice to get away from the desk and talk to people. I'm not the kind of person that often seeks out social interactions, and I think it's really good for me to be involved in various meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In academia, it often felt like I alone had to figure out how to solve a problem (or come up with an idea) in isolation to save a project that might span years. The projects I've worked on in industry are just much less stressful. They tend to be smaller or have a much longer timeline. Perhaps most importantly, they tend to have more people involved so you can always get more input. The end product isn't a research paper, so often it makes sense to be a bit less rigorous if it means a quicker turn-around (depending on the needs of the project).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, it's expected that you leave work at work. I have done small amounts of work on evenings and weekends since starting my new job, but it's seen as weird and definitely not expected. People will talk about how much they have to finish, but doing it on the weekend is still unthinkable for them. It keeps work from encroaching on my personal life, and keeps me from feeling guilty about working on other things for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Industry isn't without its problems, but I find them easier to overcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most of the time I'm interacting with more people throughout the course of a project, one downside of industry is that I have to explain things to many more non-technical people. In academic science, everyone knows some stats and some programming, so it's usually pretty easy to explain the idea behind analyses to someone regardless of their specific field. Now, I find myself talking to HR people or nurses who lack any math or programming understanding. This can lead to some frustration and talking at cross-purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the challenge of communicating with less technical people is just that - a challenge. I've always enjoyed explaining technical things in non-technical ways. It helps me to understand things when I'm forced to put it in simple terms. This is a bit more extreme - explaining sometimes complex algorithms and statistics to people who don't know the first thing about math or code. But it allows me to develop a skill to speak to a wider audience, and I think that's a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While projects are less stressful, the flip side is a feeling of less personal investment that makes it hard to feel passionate about projects. The projects can still be fun and interesting, but there isn't always a whole lot of deeper meaning in them. Relatedly, with academia, your work is in some ways open to the world. You get publications, maybe some media coverage, and are considered a recognized expert. Without going beyond your job, the same thing doesn't really happen in industry. I might get some publications due to my position, but media coverage (or any other sort of recognition outside of the company) is unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But once again, I find this issue much easier to deal with than the issues I had in academia. Though I have less passion for work projects, I have a lot more time and energy to put into my own personal projects. And this can be quite rewarding - I get to try different things, like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Potter_Overflow"&gt;coding silly twitter bots&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://tommyblanchard.com/movie-genre-ratings"&gt;writing data&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://tommyblanchard.com/does-the-muslim-ban-make-us-safer"&gt;journalism pieces&lt;/a&gt;. I find I have a wider range of projects to work on for satisfaction than I did while an academic, where I felt like any side project should ultimately net me a publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A lot of clear benefits of industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've had moments of wondering if I really did the right thing by leaving academia (usually when some reward of academia is made particularly salient). However, the thought doesn't usually last long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, I value the types of freedom an industry job gives me far more than the types academia does. I have less freedom now in terms of what specific projects I take on. However, I have much more freedom to define where I live, what industry I work in, and all of the freedoms involved in having a much more secure financial situation. There are also a number of different ways I could take my career - I could transition into a management position or stay closer to development/implementation. I could try freelancing or consulting. While I'm happy where I am right now, it's good to know that I have a lot of options for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Academia"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>Reasons I left academia</title><link href="http://tommyblanchard.com/reasons-i-left-academia" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tommy Blanchard</name></author><id>tag:tommyblanchard.com,2017-02-12:/reasons-i-left-academia</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently made the transition from academia to industry. Some people were surprised I decided to leave - I had had a pretty successful academic career. So why did I want to leave? I've read a lot of articles and opinions on reasons people leave academia. The common reasons I often …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently made the transition from academia to industry. Some people were surprised I decided to leave - I had had a pretty successful academic career. So why did I want to leave? I've read a lot of articles and opinions on reasons people leave academia. The common reasons I often saw people cite for why they decided to leave didn't resonate with me. It's usually things like that the academic job market is too tough, or that industry pays better. The better pay is certainly nice, but that wasn't an impetus for my switch. I had never really worried about the job market. So why did I decide to leave?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Becoming unhappy in academia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pretty happy during my PhD. I learned a lot throughout it, got a lot of positive feedback, felt respected, and interacted with my peers a lot. Even so, by my last year, and especially after starting my postdoc, I was slowly becoming less satisfied. Eventually I was just not happy. I became stressed out, and research wasn't fun anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I was describing my work environment to my roommate who works in industry. I told him I had maybe one to three meetings with people throughout the week. I explained that during my day, I mostly was by myself in an office. He said that sounded like it really sucked. That off-hand comment was actually really eye-opening to me. It had never occurred to me that working in such isolation probably wasn't good for me. It seemed just like the natural process of becoming more independent would of course mean more isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a postdoc or a grad student, it would often just be me and my advisor on a project. If my advisor was busy (frequently the case), it meant I was alone on the project. If others were involved in the project, in my experience their involvement was pretty superficial and communications usually occurred via email, or meetings once every month or two. It really didn't feel like I had anyone 'with me' on solving issues on a project, which was stressful. More importantly, I felt lonely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to other friends in industry reinforced the impression that it was much less isolating to work in industry than in research. They talked about frequent code-reviews and stand-up meetings. Since project turn-around was much quicker, project meetings were much more frequent. There was always a lot of interaction going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Few reasons to stay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I had pinpointed why I was feeling so unhappy, I did a lot of soul-searching on why I was so set on an academic career in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supposedly the big advantages of academia are the intellectual satisfaction of research and the freedom to research what you want. However, I didn't feel intellectually satisfied. Science works slowly, with incremental advances. Every paper I wrote was just one interpretation of one small data set about what one small brain area did in one contrived task. I was familiar with the big theories in my field, and there wasn't any new big ideas that were exciting me any more. Intellectually, focusing on such a narrow space of science was just becoming boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intellectual freedom didn't sound that exciting to me anymore. Sure, I could set up a wide range of different experiments, except 1) they had to be in line with a fundable research plan, and 2) they had to lead to publications. It seemed more like pressure to come up with good ideas than freedom to do what I want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a bit ashamed to admit that for me, the factor that made the decision difficult was the level of fame and prestige that comes with being an academic researcher. It's nice to have your name on a bunch of publications, to get some media attention, and have international colleagues that respect you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Costs of staying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My growing unhappiness forced me to really face the sacrifices I was making by staying in academia. The biggest issue for me was the cost to my personal relationships. Academia meant moving at the whims of the academic job market - due to how few jobs there are, there's little freedom in where you live geographically. Already the moves I had done for academia had cost me important relationships. There was also putting off thinking about starting a family because I didn't feel like my life was stable enough to start one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Deciding to leave&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there's a big disconnect in mentality between academia and industry because they offer very different types of rewards. In academia, all of the metrics you have for how well you're doing don't exist in industry: publications, citations, H-index, etc. Until I really started to feel the cost of academia in terms of my happiness, I never felt the allure of industry because it didn't offer me these rewards I had been trained to seek through my academic training. Similarly, it was easy to ignore the income one could make in industry because money isn't one of the big motivators in academia since (at least at the postdoc level) everyone is making about the same low amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I was forced to really open my eyes to the possibility of leaving, suddenly I had to consider what an industry job could offer me. It was painful going through the process of changing my mentality and accepting that I might never get another publication, but that was okay because publications only mean anything in academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I started learning more about data science. I learned how it would allow me to work with different data, do the parts of science I love (analysis), and give me freedom to find jobs I wanted. I thought it sounded like a much better place for me. Hopefully that judgment was right!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a retrospective on my first few months in industry and how I feel now about the move from academia. See it &lt;a href="http://tommyblanchard.com/retrospective-on-leaving-academia-for-industry-data-science"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Academia"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello, world!</title><link href="http://tommyblanchard.com/hello-world" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Tommy Blanchard</name></author><id>tag:tommyblanchard.com,2017-01-16:/hello-world</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My first post, introducing my new blog&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, I'm in the middle of the transition from academia to industry data science. This website is meant partially to replace my academic website. It's also a place for me to showcase some of my personal data science projects. I'll probably be starting with some of the small projects I've done while building up some of my data science skills, and hopefully eventually be releasing some more polished projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also intend to write blog entries (like this one). While my projects will tend to be something that involved coding, learning a new skill, and/or exploring a data set, blog entries will just be free-form writing. I mostly intend to write about data science, statistics, science, and related things. Because I've so recently come from academia, I expect many will focus on the difference between academia and industry, and the transition. And sometimes maybe I'll write about things completely unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site is still somewhat under construction, and the organization of it might change quite a bit as it grows/matures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read about the technical aspect of the blog (what tools I'm using and why), see &lt;a href="http://tommyblanchard.com/this-website"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>